Guide to the James Reid Parker Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Reid Parker papers
1879-1991
1930-1984
YCAL MSS 371
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(11 boxes)
The collection documents the career of twentieth-century American writer James Reid Parker, including his collaboration with cartoonist Helen E. Hokinson and his trusteeship of her estate. It includes drafts and printed versions of Parker's writings for The New Yorker and Woman's Day, as well as correspondence documenting his professional work, and personal correspondence and papers documenting his family relationships, family history, and military service with the Publications Branch of the Military Intelligence Service during World War II. In addition to correspondence regarding Hokinson's estate, the collection includes approximately forty-five drawings by Hokinson, chiefly for The New Yorker.
Parker, James Reid, 1909-1984
Hokinson, Helen E. (Helen Elna), 1893-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Kenneth Nesheim, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Reid Parker (1909-1984)
James Reid Parker was born in Jersey City, New Jersey, on June 2, 1909, to James A. and Rebecca Ives Parker. He received his B.A. from Lafayette College, and an M.A. in English and Comparative Literature from Columbia University in 1931. He became a regular contributor of light humorous pieces to The New Yorker magazine beginning in 1930, and wrote a column entitled "Small World," for Woman's Day from the 1940s to the early 1960s. Many of his New Yorker stories were published as anthologies, including Academic Procession and Attorneys at Law, and he published a novel, The Merry Wives of Massachusetts, in 1959. At The New Yorker, he worked closely with cartoonist Helen E. Hokinson, writing captions for her cartoons from the 1930s until her death in a plane crash in 1949. Parker served as one of the executors and trustees of Hokinson's estate, and as such published a collection of her work entitled The Hokinson Festival in 1956.
Parker married Ruth Lerrigo in 1940, and served in the Army Intelligence Service in Washington during World War II. Following the war, the Parkers lived on Nantucket for some years before moving to New York City. In the 1960s they moved to Hamden, Connecticut, where Parker died on January 27, 1984.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the career of twentieth-century American writer James Reid Parker, including his collaboration with cartoonist Helen E. Hokinson and his trusteeship of her estate. It includes drafts and printed versions of Parker's writings for The New Yorker and Woman's Day, as well as correspondence documenting his professional work, and personal correspondence and papers documenting his family relationships, family history, and military service with the Publications Branch of the Military Intelligence Service during World War II. In addition to correspondence regarding Hokinson's estate, the collection includes approximately forty-five drawings by Hokinson, chiefly for The New Yorker.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1967. II. Writings, 1919-1991. III. Personal Papers, 1879-1984. IV. Helen E. Hokinson Estate and Artwork, 1925-1990.
New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); Woman's Day; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Cartoonists -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence -- United States; Cartoons (humorous images) -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Hokinson, Helen E. (Helen Elna), 1893-1949; Parker, James Reid, 1909-1984; Parker, Rebecca Ives Kidder; Parker, Ruth Lerrigo
- Correspondence, 1918-1967; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I. is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with one folder of general correspondence filed at the end.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence documents Parker's relationships with publishers, with his collaborator Helen Hokinson, and with his family. A significant volume of letters and postcards to his wife document his experiences in Washington, D.C. during World War II. Correspondence with Helen Hokinson includes a series of postcards from Parker containing ideas for captions and cartoons gleaned from overheard conversations on a trip to California, Seattle, and Alaska in 1938. Correspondence with The New Yorker includes pay stubs and contracts.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional correspondence is filed with Series II. Writings, and includes exchanges with publishers and fan mail concerning specific works.
  - Doubleday and Company, Inc., 1944-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hokinson, Helen E. (Helen Elna), 1938-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The New Yorker, 1930-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
  - Parker, James A., 1956 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Parker, Lydia, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Parker, Rebecca Ives, 1918-1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Parker, Ruth Lerrigo, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - Parker, Ruth Lerrigo, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - Parker, Ruth Lerrigo, 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Stage, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Wodehouse, P. G. (Pelham Grenville), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General Correspondence "A-Z", 1934-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Writings, 1919-1991; Series II; 1.7; (4 boxes)
  Series II. Writings is arranged alphabetically by title, with some miscellaneous material filed at the end.
  Series II. documents Parker's writing career, and includes drafts and printed versions of stories, articles, and plays; correspondence from publishers and fans; contracts for books anthologizing his stories; notebooks; and some early poems and school essays.
  - Academic Procession
    - Correspondence and background material, 1937-1952 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Reviews, circa 1937 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Fan mail, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      General note
      Includes letters from Harold W. Ross and Katharine S. White.
  - Attorneys at Law: Forbes, Hathaway, Bryan & Devore
    - Correspondence and documents, 1940-1991 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Reviews, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - Fan mail, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
      Includes letters from Harold W. Ross, Katharine S. White, and Alexander Woollcot.
  - "Friends, Americans, Countrymen!", typescript draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
  - "The Happier We'll Be," contract, 1959 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Madame President: A Comedy in Three Acts", drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
  - The Merry Wives of Massachusetts
    - Correspondence and documents, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Reviews, circa 1959 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Fan mail, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - The New Yorker, tearsheets and drafts, 1931-1945 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Open House
    - Reviews, circa 1951 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
    - Fan mail, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - The Pleasure Was Mine
    - Correspondence and documents, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Reviews, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "Problem Child," drafts, typescript and typescript, corrected, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "Remember that You are not in America," typescript draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - "The Social Satire in the Savoy Operas," Master's thesis, Columbia University, bound typescript, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - "Small World" column in Woman's Day
    - Drafts, proofs, tearsheets, reprint, and 1 full issue (December 1949), 1948-1963 (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
    - Illustration, pen and ink, 1947 October (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence including fan mail, 1951-1954 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - "State of Grace", typescript draft, contract, and correspondence, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - "The Way to Behave", typescript draft, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous tear sheets, 1935-1951 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 60-65)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 6, Folder 66-72)
  - School essays, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Poems, 1919, undated (Box 6, Folder 74-75)
- Personal Papers, 1879-1984; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Series III. is arranged roughly chronologically.
  Series III. Personal Papers consists of legal and financial documents, photographs of Parker (chiefly publicity head shots), and genealogical information. Most extensively documented in this series is Parker's service in the Publications Branch of the Military Intelligence Service during World War II. These papers include a copy of a 1942 report on "The German Campaign in Norway," accompanied by photographs.
  - "The Revolutionary Adams Ancestry of Rebecca Ives Parker", 1879, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
    Includes photographs of family homes and unidentified women.
  - Photographs of James Reid Parker, 1911-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 77-79)
  - "The Queen's Husband," review of dramatic performance, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Military service (Military Intelligence Service: Publications Branch), 1942-1947 (Box 6, Folder 81-85)
  - Tax forms and other financial documentation, 1942-1947 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Estate of Rebecca Ives Parker, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Leases, New York and Nantucket, 1950-1959 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Estates of Edmund Parker, James A. Parker, and Lydia Parker, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Notes and ephemera from trip to Great Britain, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Miscellaneous notes and ephemera, 1963-1983, undated (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Passports, 1967-1979 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Social Security Administration, 1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Obituaries, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 94)
- Helen E. Hokinson Estate and Artwork, 1925-1990; Series IV; 0.6; (3 boxes)
  Series IV. is arranged by format and size.
  Series IV. consists of estate paperwork and drawings. Estate paperwork documents the work of the executors and trustees to disperse and manage Hokinson's assets and to manage the rights to her artwork. It includes information about exhibits of Hokinsons's work and the estate's publication of a compilation of her cartoons, The Hokinson Festival, in 1956. Artwork includes a mix of preliminary sketches, drafts, final versions, and proofs for New Yorker covers and cartoons. Captioned cartoons are chiefly ink and wash drawings, while drawings intended for the cover are watercolors.
  - Estate of Helen E. Hokinson, legal correspondence and documents, 1949-1956, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 95-100)
  - Obituaries, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Artwork
    - Sketches and Christmas cards, 1943, undated (Box 7, Folder 102-103)
    - Captioned cartoon, undated (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Captioned cartoons, undated (Box 8, Folder 105-121)
    - Cover art for The New Yorker, 1932-1949, undated (Box 9, Folder 122-135)
    - Other artwork
      - Uncaptioned cartoons and sketches, 1925, undated (Box 9, Folder 136-139)
        Includes sketch published in the July 4, 1925 issue of The New Yorker, and one cartoon not by Hokinson.
      - "Personal sketch of Chilean Pianist Claudio Arrau, not in the New York[er]", undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
- Oversize
  - Photographs of James Reid Parker (in Series III), undated (Box 9, Folder 141)